Hi everyone, welcome. Thanks for joining
us. My name is Robert. I will be your
host. This is George Caleb Bingham, the
Missouri artist, the latest of our
programs on the American Experience,
which features great American art
through the course of time. And tonight
we're going to be talking about George
Caleb Bingham, one of the great American
artists of the mid 1800s. He was based
in Missouri. In fact, he's known as the
Missouri artist and he's known for doing
a wide variety of genre type paintings,
particularly his river series and then
also his election series, but he also
did portraits and history paintings and
various other things like that. So,
we're going to check his art out. Uh, a
little bit about George Caleb before we
begin. He was born in 1811. He passed
away in 1879.
He was known as the Missouri artist and
he painted the western frontier uh which
at that time was in Missouri. Uh the
country had not extended as far west as
it later would. And he's kind of known
as the um pain of the western frontier.
He's also a promoter of kind of this uh
idea of the American national identity
during the mid 1800s. Like what exactly
does America mean and was it all about?
Um and Bingham is documenting that
through his paintings. uh his subjects
mostly known for his river series and
other series he did on country elections
he did history paintings genre scenes
and portraits he was mostly a
self-taught artist and interestingly
enough he also was a local Missouri
politician so we'll dive a little bit
more in that in just a moment but first
we'll introduce ourselves our panel my
name is Robert I'll be your host I'm
riggie from Detroit Michigan I was an
art history major at the University of
Michigan and spent the first two years
of my career fortunately working at a
fabulous museum, the Detroit Institute
of Arts before transitioning off into
the business world. And my favorite
artist, I'll go with how about the topic
of our next set of discussions,
Frederick Remington. And we also have
our good friend Patty, the pride of
Portsouth, New Hampshire, joining us
tonight. Hi, Patty. How are you? Want to
introduce yourself and who's your
favorite artist?
>> Uh, I'm doing well. It's been an
interesting day, a very exciting day,
thanks to you. And um let's see. I'm
gonna I'm I've been stuck on George
O'Keefe for a while. I we've just been
doing a lot of work on her and she
sticks for a lot of reasons.
>> Okay. Well, that's fabulous. Well, thank
you. And um let's see. You saw the film
last night and then this program and we
did it once before. Any particular um
advice or recommendations you give to
people as they're looking at the art of
George Caleb Bingham? Well, as I had
mentioned last night, he was a
contemporary of Mark Twain a little bit
earlier, but um they overlapped. He was
born within 40 years of when America
bea became America as opposed to being a
colony of England. So I was kind of
there was an image sort of came to me
last night. Um so if you think of the
eastern seabboard where the 13 original
colonies were the whole focus of that
history is eastward toward Britain and
Europe and suddenly especially once
Jefferson purchased the Louisiana
Purchase, you had an American identity
that was now looking westward as as
opposed to eastward. and um both Twain
and um Bingham uh kind of uh established
that identity um in a lot of ways and we
still look back on both of them. I think
I had said last night like Bingham could
have been an illustrator for Mark Twain.
They were that close in terms of a lot
of their perceptions about the
developing country um and this
particular part of the country as well,
but they both started. Um, but yeah,
it's it's like a almost like a chapter.
If you were to look at the map of the
United States, you could almost divide
it into segments moving westward. Other
than, of course, California had a head
start with the Spanish settlement, but
um it just I don't know why that image
sort of came to me, but it really is a
very valuable he he offers a lot of
insight as to how America saw itself and
how it became the America it was
becoming.
Okay. Oh, excellent. I like that.
Looking west instead of east. Thank you.
I appreciate that. And we also have our
good friend Brad joining us. Brad's the
pride of Falling Waters, West Virginia.
Hi, Brad. You want to introduce yourself
and who's your favorite artist?
>> Sure. My uh Well, I'm Brad. You know
where I'm from now? Uh my favorite
artist
>> Where is Falling Waters, West Virginia
for people that might not be familiar
with that geography?
>> Eastern West Virginia, right? It It's
almost metropolitan DC. Not quite. It's
a little too far to be metropolitan DC,
but it's maybe 70 miles from DC.
So, it's the very eastern part of West
Virginia.
>> Okay. And then, um, do you have a
favorite artist?
>> Yes, I do. I would I would have to say
Andrew Wyth at this point.
>> Oh, I like Andrew W. Actually, like the
whole Wyatt family.
>> Yeah, the Well, the family, but if I
have to pick one.
>> Okay, excellent. Well, thanks, Brad. I
appreciate that. And I also have my good
friend Harry joining us. Hi Harry. Can
you hear me? Okay.
>> Uh yeah, loud and clear.
>> Harry, I can't remember what exact city
you live in in Northern Virginia, so
we'll just call you the the pride of
Northern Virginia. How's that? And um
you want to introduce yourself and and
who's your favorite artist? By
>> the way, Harry and I have been friends
for 10 and a half years. How about that?
>> How about that? Um I'm I'm actually in
Sterling uh which is about 20 miles uh
west of Washington DC uh near out near
Dallas airport and um I'm going to say
my the last tour I did um last month was
at the portrait gallery and I'm gonna
the the two artists whose paintings are
part of that tour were are Eastman
Johnson and Winslow Homer and uh I you
know I I was thinking again about their
work um because I uh was able to show
other people
that was a tour on Civil War era uh
painting. So
>> Oh, that's awesome. We did a program on
Winsow Homer a while back. It's on our
YouTube channel. Um Eastman Johnson, not
as well known. I like him a lot too. Um
great kind of Civil War era painter. Um
and he actually lived in Washington DC
for a number of years. So kudos to you
for introducing people more to that. Um
do you have any just out of curiosity
any upcoming tours you're going to be
doing in Washington DC?
>> Well um I don't think I'm going to get
to anything this month. Um in I have two
potential tours for August, but it
depends on my schedule and the weather.
Um
the uh but I could potentially do a a
Watergate tour uh cuz August is the
month that President Nixon resigned. Uh
so that's you know sort of connected and
uh also the uh the burning of Washington
in 1814 by the British took place in at
the end of August.
So those are two potential tours for the
month of August.
>> Oh, that's awesome. Harry, I hope you
host both of those or at least one.
That's awesome. Thank you so much for
being here. All right, let's go ahead
and get started. Um, so this is a whole
series of programs we've been doing on
American art and American artists. And
it's part of what we'd call say the
quote unquote American experience. Um,
and what I mean by that is I really like
art and I really like history and I like
how the two were interconnected with one
another. So for instance um in America
during this time you have artists that
are visually documenting and recording
uh what's going on in American history
so that people like us in 2025 can look
back and see what was happening. Uh and
then also too you have artists really
inspiring and influencing American
popular culture. So you really see both
of those things with the artwork we're
going to be looking at tonight. George
Caleb Bingham. So something for you to
keep in mind. and Bingham. A little bit
of biographical information for him was
before we start looking at his art. He
was actually born in the Shannondoa
Valley, a place where I used to live
many, many years ago. And in Augusta
County, and he was born in 1811, and
then when he was a young boy, his family
moved from
Virginia to Missouri. kind of like what
Patty was talking about a little bit
earlier where you have this um thought
where instead of looking towards the
east towards Europe people are looking
towards the west uh in all this land of
opportunity and interestingly enough if
you go back to okay so Bingham's family
moves to Missouri in 1819 uh you know
that wasn't long after the Louiswis and
Clark expedition it had only ended 13
years earlier Um, so that's really not
that long ago. Um, and so I think maybe
for a lot of people when they think of
Missouri, uh, they think of kind of
middle America and the West, so to
speak, is beyond that. But that is true,
but that wasn't the case at this point
in time in the early 1800s. This was the
West. And this was kind of as far out as
the United States went. And in fact,
when the family moved to Missouri, it
wasn't even a state yet. They moved
there in 1819 and Missouri didn't become
a state uh until 1821. So there's
Missouri right there on the map,
formerly part of the Missouri territory.
And then just kind of a quick historical
context overview. You know, Missouri is
a big state. A lot of people live there.
It's got two big metropolitan areas with
St. Louis and Kansas City. It was a very
different type of place when the Bingham
family moved there. Um so they arrived
again in 1819. there was really only
about 60some thousand people living in
the whole state. Uh that would be the
size of a city now. Um they didn't get
statehood until 1821. Missouri is the
24th state. And then Bingham's art
career begins in 1834. That's kind of
noteworthy because he's trying to
support himself as an artist uh in a
state that doesn't really have a lot of
people. Uh it's hard to become an artist
in any type of uh environment
geographically, but even more so if
there's just not a lot of people
available. that he's able to carve out a
career
and how his art career begins. This is a
really interesting story. There was a
American portrait painter by the name of
Chester Harding was born in 1792 and he
just happens to be traveling through
Missouri one day and he stays at a
boarding house that just happened to be
owned by George Caleb Bingham's family.
Um, and so this is taking place in 1820.
That's a self-portrait of Harding on the
left. And Harding is doing a portrait of
Daniel Boone. At this point in time,
Daniel Boone uh was in the final months
of his life. Uh Harding ends up doing a
painted portrait of him. Of course, this
is before photography.
And so he's doing this depiction of this
great American. He just so happens to be
painting it at the boarding house. Now,
Boon wasn't actually there at the time.
um he's doing the he did kind of the
rough work earlier and he's kind of
finishing things up. But that being
said, a young George Caleb Bingham got
to see this and it really kind of sparks
his interest in art. So kind of an
unusual start for his um artistic
career. Bingham decides he wants to be
an artist. That's what he ends up doing.
We'll go look at his artworks and we'll
do it mostly like a chronological order
just so you can see how things change
and develop and evolve over time. And
Bingham starts his career as a portrait
painter. And one of the first portraits
he did was a self-portrait, a picture of
himself. This is when he was only 23 or
24 years old. He had some other jobs
that he was doing before he became a
full-time artist. He was an apprentice
um like cabinet maker and I don't know
was involved in like different types of
endeavors um while he was trying to
support himself as an artist early on.
and he actually ends up making four
self-portraits. Uh this is the first of
those four and he makes approximately
500 self-portraits that we know of
during his career. So he was very
prolific in that regard and again
noteworthy that he's able to do this um
while not living in say New York City or
someplace like that where they have more
people available.
And then here is the museum card for
this painting. The fine handling of line
and paint in this self-portrait are
remarkable achievements for a young
23-year-old artist. Missurian George
Caleb Bingham had no formal training or
even substantial exposure to fine art at
this point in his career. He presents
himself in a straightforward style as
one of the many members of the growing
middle class in Missouri, then
considered the country's far west.
And there's Bingham really talented
portrait um especially for such early
point in his career.
And then let's look at some of these
other portraits that he did. Um you
know, one of the things that's really
important for an artist is to get
commissions. And he ends up meeting a
guy uh by the name of James Rollins who
not only becomes friends with him, uh he
becomes an important patron for
Binghams. and he introduces him to a lot
of other uh well-known wealthy prominent
people in the area and then Bingham ends
up getting a lot of commissions from
these so-called friends of Rollins. Um
but he paints Rollins several times
during their lives together. Um here is
a portrait that he did of him 1834. So
very important friend and patron for
networking.
And so again, at this point in time,
he's kind of traveling around central
Missouri doing portraits of different
individuals, sometimes um families, like
a married couple. So this is a portrait
of a husband who was a merchant. And
then here is a companion portrait of his
wife
done in the same year, 1835.
Now, this is an era before photography
has really gotten going back in 1835.
And a lot of times what people would do
in this era is they would get portraits
made not only to kind of preserve the
memory of themselves, but kind of also
to show off their wealth. So usually
what people do at this point in time in
history is they'd get these paintings
made, these oil paintings, and they'd
hang them in their parlor, and then when
people would come over to visit them,
they could see them. And if you saw this
on the wall, it was kind of like a
status symbol to a certain degree
because you'd have to have a fair amount
of money um to be able to hire a painter
to do your portrait. Um and it also kind
of shows off kind of like a certain
level of sophistication like, "Oh yeah,
I hang out with artists and I'm having
my oil portrait done." Uh type of thing.
And so that's kind of the dual purpose
of these is kind of one to preserve the
people's image, but also to kind of show
off their wealth and status and
intelligence and all that kind of stuff.
Um, so again, here's some more examples
of portraits. This was a judge from
Columbia, Missouri.
Here's the judge's wife.
Here they are side by side. I love
looking at these fashions from people
back in the day. Um, Patty will note
that they don't have the um the shoulder
pads just yet. That's coming up
century and a half later.
But anyway, um the judge and his wife.
And then he does get a little bit more
advanced in terms of like his
portraiture u making ones that are more
complex. This one is actually
interesting one. I've seen this up
close. It actually is in the state
department in Washington DC. you know,
like the Department of State, the State
Department, the diplomatic uh group of
the United States government, they have
a building or an area of the building
called the diplomatic reception rooms.
This painting hangs in there.
And then this is an interesting one.
This one's not very well known. I think
partially because it's not in a museum.
It's in a private collection. So, I
don't have a great uh photo of this one
because it's not in a particular museum
collection. But that being said, I
really like this painting a lot. called
Family Life on the Frontier. It was made
sometime before 1840
and it kind of looks like uh you know
the depiction of hey this is what family
life uh in middle America was like at
this point in time that people reading
by candle light and the fireplace and um
all this kind of stuff. So let me stop
there for a moment and see if our
distinguished panelists Harry Patty and
Brad have any thoughts on either the
portraits or this painting or George
Caleb being up until now. So, any of the
three of you have anything you want to
chime in with?
>> One thing I like about this one is that
it isn't portraying a middle class. It's
portraying
um the grit of what this settlement of
this new area was about. This, you can
see it's very dark. There's not a lot of
windows. Um it's not heavily furnished.
So, it it he's including that's what I
mean by the storytelling aspect of it.
It's like it's building an image of who
these people were.
>> Oh, that's a great point, Patty. Thanks
for mentioning that because yeah, I
mean, if you look at these previous
people he's depicting. I mean, these
people are kind of the high society
people of central Missouri. Um, and
these are not the same people that are
being depicted. This is a little bit uh
harder of a life um than what we would
have seen kind of the fine finery in the
previous portraits,
>> but they certainly have an incredibly
bright light on the table.
>> Yeah, I know. I was uh wondering what
the source of that was.
>> I didn't like candles burn that right.
Maybe he's got the flashlight on his
iPhone feature turned up.
>> LED lights.
>> What about Harry? Any
>> thoughts on the Bingham paintings up
until now?
>> Well, ju just on his early life. Um, you
know, Patty mentioned Mark Twain who's
uh a little bit younger. Um, the other
contemporary of theirs is Abraham
Lincoln. And, you know, he's born in
Kentucky and has very little formal
education. I think Twain left school uh
in the fifth grade or something. Um, and
yet became a fabulous writer. And here
we have a a painter who um, you know, is
is really self-taught. I mean he goes to
Europe later in life after you know he
establishes him himself as an artist to
to you know understand the history of
painting but um he really has no uh
background e except looking at other you
know frontier artists um who who he's
taking his cues from and uh I I think
that's you know it's sort of an
interesting story from that that era,
right, where you where you had people
who ended up doing accomplishing really
uh amazing things with very little
formal training.
>> Oh, yeah. And it's funny that you
mentioned Abraham Lincoln because this
painting actually reminds me of Abraham
Lincoln, although um Lincoln's
upbringing, I think, was uh much uh
let's see, poor or not as I mean, these
people aren't rich. Um, but Lincoln was
really, really poor when he was growing
up. But for some reason, this painting
does always remind me of Abraham
Lincoln. So, kind of funny that you
mentioned that, Harry.
>> Yeah, I like that. I like that you made
that connection, too. And they do have a
great deal in common as Americans.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah, I would agree with that.
All right. Well, let's continue on. Um,
let's see. So, here's another portrait.
This was a doctor, a friend of his. And
you'll notice, okay, so um the earlier
portraits that we saw of Bingham started
in like 1834. This is 10 years later.
And you can see this is he's pretty
advanced in terms of his skill,
especially for someone that um never
really had any formal training. As Harry
mentioned, he didn't really see a lot of
other I mean, it's not like he can walk
down to the Metropolit Museum of Art and
go look at, you know, Van Go and Monae
paintings and stuff. Um he's kind of
looking at art from studying like
magazines and prints and stuff like
that. So pretty extraordinary um
development in that regard. And then um
somewhat early on in his life, Bingham
ends up going to Washington DC. He's
wants to be a professional artist or he
is a professional artist. Um it requires
a certain amount of level of uh say
sophistication and economic resources to
be able to have your painted portrait
done. Uh and he's thinking, you know
what, there's a lot of prominent wealthy
people in Washington DC. Uh, so if I
want to be a portrait painter, that's
probably a lot better place to be than
central Missouri. So he ends up moving
to Washington DC. And he actually does
get a lot of commissions um from say
famous people, at least historically,
prominent people. So he does a portrait
of John Quincy Adams. He did this one
initially in 1844
and then Adams passed away in 1848. Um
and Adams was greatly admired in the uh
mid 1800s as like a man of virtue. Uh
after he lost the presidency, he was in
Congress, was very well respected. And
when he passed away, there was a um big
interest in his life. And so um Caleb
Bingham made this essentially a copy of
an earlier portrait he did. And then
this is Daniel Webster, important
politician from the mid 1800s from
Massachusetts. And so, um, Bingham ends
up living in Washington DC for four
years, interestingly enough. So, he
wasn't always in Missouri.
And then here's an interesting portrait.
This was a congressman and future
governor from Missouri. Uh, this one a
little bit more advanced. It's a full
portrait. He's not just showing the
person's face and their um like upper
torso. He's got like the full body with
like some background stuff. So, kind of
interesting development there.
And then this is the picture of his
first wife. Um, Bingham ended up being
married three times, which uh maybe
that's not uncommon today. Um, that
actually wasn't that uncommon back then
just because people's spouses tend to
not live a long time or people just in
general didn't live a long time and if
you were married, it wasn't uncommon for
your spouse to pass away. Um, and so
people would frequently remarry or
remarried more than once. Um so this was
his first wife Sarah Elizabeth.
They ended up marrying
um in 1836.
Uh now interestingly enough with this
portrait his son is depicted here um
although his son passed away the year
prior and so the thought is maybe this
was like a memorial picture to his son
and then also to his first wife which he
included in there.
And then this is also his first wife.
Now again, notice this is a portrait um
of her, although it's not officially
titled as a portrait, but it's a little
bit more advanced than some of the
previous things that we've seen. And
this was part of his Washington DC years
>> and she's reading a book and it looks
like the book wasn't that exciting. So I
think it might have been an accounting
book because I read these and they put
me to sleep every time also. So
or it would have been something else.
Who knows? But anyway, a really nice
portrait, touching a touching portrait
of his wife. Um, and then here's a
marriage portrait. This young lady was
getting married. It's frequent during
this era u before photography becomes
prominent for people to have a painted
portrait of themselves either um right
after they got engaged um or right after
they got married. That was the case
here.
And again, you can see the talent of his
abilities as a portrait painter. Um, so
next we'll talk about this river series.
Um, but before we do that, any final
thoughts on the portraits from our panel
of guests?
I think the one um he did of the the
Missouri politician, the placement was
interesting because the not only is it a
fulllength portrait of the man, but he
dwarfs the um Capitol building behind
him and
>> yeah, that's kind of a um not uncommon
thing from this era just because like
now if you were taking like a selfie or
something, yeah, you'd get real close
and it'd be prominent in the background,
but it was it was kind of almost like,
oh, he's including including that in
here just so you know that this guy's a
politician. Um, but yeah, that is an
interesting observation because you do
frequently see that in like paintings
from this era.
>> Interesting.
>> Anything else?
>> I was just going to mention the the the
painting of the the woman in the white
gown in the chair. um you know he has
obviously
traveled some now and seen other artists
and other paintings because you know a
lot of the early portraits are you know
what you might expect you know painting
in a frontier towns uh in the west but
this is a painting which where an artist
has either seen or
has seen other artists that are looking
at European paintings
Right.
>> Yeah. Like if you contrast this these
two, which I like these,
>> right? Like this is these portraits, you
know, he's doing very lifelike uh and
you know, not much of a background, dark
clothing or or the blue scarf, you know,
what the people would actually be
wearing. Uh whereas in that portrait um
you know he's got the curtain, there's a
little column and and there's you know
some uh fabric on the chair uh and the
beautiful folds in in her dress. he he
has seen either European paintings or
Americans who are working on European
painting models um because this is a
much more sophisticated
uh sort of you know eastwardlooking
uh sort of image.
>> Yeah, that's a great point um as well.
>> Excellent. Yeah,
>> if you look at the previous couple that
the I the thought that keeps coming into
my mind is homespun
[Laughter]
that woman and man that you showed in
the previous slide it home.
>> Uhhuh.
>> Yeah. Sort of like that that rough
fabric people would make.
>> Oh yeah. And then even the portrait of
himself, the self-portrait. I mean this
is really nicely done too. Um but like
it's like Harry's bringing up the other
ones are like a whole different
dimension. Exactly. Nice.
>> Brad, what about you? Any thoughts on
the portraits before we continue on?
All right. Well, let's go to the river
series. So, this is what um Bingham is
most well known for. He made these
paintings and they were super popular.
Um he ended up making a lot of money
from selling these. um in business or in
marketing they have this thing this
concept called like the big idea where
you think of something it ends up being
hugely successful. Um so this was his
big idea. No one had really done
anything like this before. He ends up
making these river paintings and uhund
and some years later we're still talking
about these. So let's discuss this. So
Bingham's home is in central north
central Missouri. Here's Kansas City.
Here's St. Louis.
And he's living though right along the
Missouri River, which uh I always feel
like the Missouri River doesn't get its
due credit. Everybody in America has
heard of the Mississippi River. Um but
the Missouri River is also very
important. And Bingham's home is in
central Missouri. You can actually visit
it. It's a museum open to the public.
It's part of the Arrow Rock State
Historic Park. Uh he lived there from
1837 to 1845. If you get a chance, you
should go visit this site. not only can
learn about Bingham, but how people
lived in the mid 1800s in Missouri. And
this was actually a pretty nice home. Uh
it's got bricks and windows and things
like that. So, uh he was doing fairly
well uh selling his portraits at this
point in time.
And if you visit this site, they have a
lot of really cool uh living history
programs. You can get a sense of what it
would have been like uh to live in this
era at this point in time.
And then again, when I think when people
think of the American West, they think
of cowboys and Indians and soldiers and
all this stuff. And that is a real
thing, but that's like a couple
generations later. That's like after the
Civil War, like 1870s, 1880s. We're
talking about the 1830s and 1840s. Um,
so like Frederick Remington who going to
be featuring in early September. Um, his
artwork is I think kind of synonymous
today with the American West, but that's
further west and that's like a few
decades later. So, we're not quite there
yet. At this point in time, this is the
American West because this is really as
far as at least the United States
extends. Of course, there's um
indigenous people that are living
further west and even within some of
these areas um where Bingham is at. But
that being said, this is kind of the end
of the United States where he's at at
this point in time.
And he ends up making this painting,
which is uh one of his more famous
works. It's called Fur Traders
Descending the Missouri. It's from 1845.
It's part of his river series where he's
depicting uh people living and working
along the Mississippi and Missouri
rivers. This is a really iconic
painting. If you had to uh make a list
of famous American paintings uh that
have been created through the course of
time, I can guarantee you that this one
would be on that list. Uh and
interesting enough, this painting was
actually lost for several years and
rediscovered was rediscovered in the
early 1900s by the Metropolitan Museum
of Art. And here it is. And you have
these two figures and they're in this
dugout canoe and they're traveling along
a river and they have some type of black
animal that no one is quite sure what
that is. If it's a cat or a raccoon or
who knows what. Um let's see. So I'm
going to play a short video um a video
clip of the Bingham painting. This one
being rediscovered. So it was discovered
um by a employee of the Metropolitan
Museum Art. So, I'm going to play a clip
from this video. Um, but I have to pause
our recording because I don't want to
get into trouble with the copyright
police. So, let me pause this for a
second.
Okay. So, this painting was lost for a
while. Um, was just kind of floating
around and ended up in the store. Uh,
the Met buys it. And there's actually
two versions of the painting. There's
one at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in
New York, which is done in 1845. There's
another version similar but a little bit
different at the Detroit Institute of
Arts, my former employer, which was made
in 1851. And you're familiar with this
concept where they make a movie and it's
really successful, so they end up doing
a sequel. Well, artists do the same
thing. They have a successful painting
that's popular and they frequently will
make other versions of the painting
later on down the road. That's what
Bingham ends up doing here.
And so this is again for traders
descending to Missouri. So 1845.
It's at the Metropolitan Museum of Art
in New York.
And then here's one at the Detroit
Institute of Art. It's called The
Trappers Return from 1851.
So here's the New York version.
Here's the DIA version.
And here they are side by side. Now, a
few things to point out about this. Um,
first of all, by the time Bingham paints
these works, this kind of way of life
had really disappeared. This was kind of
a scene that he remembered more from his
childhood where he'd see these uh fur
trappers descending the river. Uh, this
wasn't really a thing that was going on
um at this point in time, but you know,
that's fine. It doesn't need to uh be
exactly in the historical moment for it
to be important work. Uh, but the fur
trade does play a really important part
of the history of the American West. Um,
it's really kind of a vanishing way of
life though at this point in time and a
lot of like art historians have really
uh commented on the fact that this is a
great example of what's known as
luminism uh where there's a landscape
that's beautifully lit uh captured in a
painting.
>> Robert, can I interrupt you a second?
>> Yes, of course. Always.
>> Seems to me that we're seeing u an image
of the movie stopped, not any of the
others that you've been talking about.
Oh, really? H Okay.
>> Oh, that's weird. Um, well, here, let me
do this. Let me stop that.
Let me start up. Thanks, Brad. I
appreciate that. But yeah, feel free to
chime in as always.
Hold on for one second.
I think we're back to having those
ghosts from the live a causing us
technical problems.
Okay, here it goes. Um, let's see. Well,
let me go back a second in case we
missed this.
All right, so here's the one that's in
New York at the Met. Here's the one
that's in Detroit.
And here's the two side by side. Again,
this was kind of a way of life that
would pretty much mostly disappear by
the time Bingham paints this, but that's
okay.
And then here is the museum info card
for this painting
at the Museum in Detroit. Raised in
central Missouri, Bingham found the most
enduring subjects of his art in the
trappers and boatman who populated his
state's great rivers, the Missouri and
the Mississippi. Combining the elements
of water, foliage, hazy morning light,
rivermen and their simple crafts, he
created a sequence known today as the
river paintings. He didn't call it that.
That's what art historians categorized
it later on uh after his passing. The
trapper's return is generally considered
one of the artist's finest works. The
picture presents a dugout canoe moving
slowly downstream with an old French
trader paddling in the stern and his son
mid ships with an animal on the bow.
And again, the Mississippi River is so
much more well known in the United
States. But that being said, the
Missouri River is also extremely
important. See, it's extremely long.
2,341
miles.
Here's the two paintings side by side.
Oops. There's always been a big debate
on um what this animal is on the left,
and there is no one that knows 100% for
sure. I've people, oh, it's a cat, it's
a raccoon, it's a who knows what. But I
really don't want to get hung up on what
the animal is. Uh because actually the
more important part uh is the actual two
traders themselves. So, you have this
kind of uh uh older gentleman looking
very stern. He's paddling the canoe.
This is probably either um supplies that
they need for their trip or probably
more likely furs uh and this is
supposedly his son and they're traveling
down the river. They've probably traded
for furs uh with Native Americans and
they're taking these or transporting
them to um say United States American
citizen encampments and they'll trade
them for money and things like that. Um,
let's see. Let's check in with Harry,
Patty, and Brad. Any thoughts on the
Trappers Return set of paintings?
One thing I always think of when you
show either of these um in closeup is
that without saying anything about it,
but between the clothing of the um older
gentleman and the um just the general
look of the of the younger one, um the
suggestion is here of um the interaction
between uh early Americans and Native
Americans.
Um, it's subtle though. I mean, I only
think about it when I'm looking at it
and contemplating it.
>> Oh, yeah. Definitely.
>> Go ahead.
>> Oh, I was going to say, yeah,
definitely. I mean, that his um the
younger person is thought to be a mixed
race individual between the trapper and
indigenous woman. And that was a common
thing because it kind of strengthened
the bonds between these fur traders and
the indigenous peoples. Um, so yeah,
it's more subtle kind of um connection.
>> It sounds Yeah, but it's implied.
Exactly.
>> Yeah, implied, right? Exactly. Um, so
that's cool. What about you, Brad Harry?
Any thoughts on this set?
>> Well, actually, um, the New York
painting, his original title was French
trader dash halfbreed son.
>> Oh, okay.
>> So, it it wasn't subtle in the title.
>> Yeah. They didn't they didn't think that
was politically correct. And so at some
point in time that title got changed.
>> The the American art or you know the
museum that bought it actually changed
the title before exhibiting it
>> um thinking that that would be less
controversial. But um so yeah, I mean
I mean the other interesting thing about
the painting itself is that
you know it it's kind of it we would
call it a genre painting but it's sort
of a combination of portrait and
landscape, right? Because the figures
are looking right at us,
>> right? It it's not like we're observing
two guys, you know, rowing down the
river, right? We're looking at two guys
who stopped their boat to look at us,
>> right?
>> Or we called out to them and said,
"Hey," you know,
>> uh, and they stopped and looked right at
us.
>> And even their pet is looking right at
>> What's wrong?
>> How far to Montana?
>> Exactly. So it it's it's a little bit
different than just, you know, observing
a landscape, right? It it's almost like
we as the observers are interacting with
the the the men on the boat. Um and uh
you know, it gives it kind of an
intimate quality like, hey, we're we're
we're right there with them on the
river.
>> Yeah. Imagine how different it would be
if neither of the two figures were
looking at us. If they like the guy was
looking straight ahead and the younger
boy or young man was looking at him or
looking the other way or something would
be a very different type of painting.
>> Yeah. That you can't not look at
especially the first one I they're very
similar but the first one Harry's right
it just grabs you. It's like you have to
look back because you're being looked
at.
All right, let's continue on.
>> Yeah, and that that I was just going to
say that New York the that that
landscape, you know, it it's so
just the mist and and you know, you
can't quite make out the details. It
looks like an island in the river. It's
really It's quite beautiful.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah, the landscaping
itself is really nice, which is funny
because he's not known as a landscape
painter, although he did paint some um
landscapes. All right, let's continue
on. This is perhaps uh another one of
his most famous paintings, the Jolly
Flatb. And this is not far from where
Harry and Brad Arts at the National
Gallery Art in Washington DC painted in
1846. It's another example of a genre of
painting. We'll explain what exactly
that term means just a minute. Um, and
this series of art programs you do about
American art artists, um, it really
tends to kind of uncover some of the
facts of the American experience. And
so, in particular, uh, one of the things
that really benefited the United States
during the mid 1800s and even later, uh,
was having this river system, the
Missouri River, the, um, Mississippi
River, the Ohio River, etc. Uh, and this
painting has an interesting connection
to Abraham Lincoln. We talking about him
again. Music, dancing, relaxing. These
men are enjoying themselves as they
navigate a flatbo down what is likely
the Missouri River, the longest river in
North America. In the early 1800s, goods
and people moved via a network of
waterways across the country. Flatboats
were rectangular vessels designed to
carry large loads of cargo. George Caleb
Bingham, a self-taught artist, lived
near the Missouri River and depicted the
culture of trappers and boers in his
paintings.
And here's the work full view. So, it's
a bunch of guys. They're on this flatbo.
They're going down the river. Uh, some
of them are playing music and one of the
guys is dancing.
Here's a closeup.
And notice some of the figures appear to
be looking at us again, although some of
the others are oblivious to it.
And then I thought you might be
wondering what kind of music did people
listen to at this point in time. So let
me stop the video or pause the video for
a second so I don't get into copyright
trouble and I'll play a song that was
really popular during this point in time
in history and it's one that you may
have heard of before. So
and then we've been talking about genre
paintings and what exactly does that
mean? Uh, genre painting is an art form
that depicts aspects of everyday life by
portraying ordinary people engaged in
common activities. One classic
definition of a genre scene is that it
shows figures to whom no identity can be
attached either individually or
collectively, thus distinguishing it
from history paintings and portraits. So
for instance, we don't know who any of
these guys are in this painting. And
Bingham created many genre paintings
during his career. So we'll use that
term throughout our program.
Uh, so what
>> one of the points that was made film
last night um was that he traveled
around with costume type
um equipment, clothing and things so
that he could dress people up to paint
these genres.
>> Oh yeah, he can kind of modify him if
he's not completely if they don't quite
fit the uh character that he's looking
for. That's a great point. Um let's see.
And then what kind of transportation
options did people have uh in an era
before railroads and automobiles? Well,
you could walk, you could um ride a
horse, you could push a cart, you could
use this uh wagon that they have at the
Smithsonian American History Museum. And
so this was a very slow way of
transporting stuff and very laborious
and you can only take so much at a time
and uh you need animals to haul this
stuff. uh a lot quicker, efficient way
to do things would be to use the river.
Now, they didn't have steam power at
this point in time, but they could use
the current of the river or try and
steer a boat and things like that. So,
what you have is in these northern
areas, they're loading up these flat
boats with stuff and they're basically
um drifting them down the river to point
south. and sometimes they would go all
the way to New Orleans.
And the Mississippi and Missouri River
economics really plays a huge um role in
the economic development of the United
States because it really increased the
amount of commerce and trade and
economic activity and things like that.
Uh really has a big impact on the
development and economic growth of the
United States. And so some of these
boats were pretty basic. Um, I've read
accounts where one or two guys working
for a while could put one of these
together. Um, and then if some of them
would be a little bit more advanced, you
could even take horses with you. Uh, of
course, you would pack up some food. So,
oftentimes they were loading up like
manufactured goods or agricultural
products and things like that. They're
sending them down the river as far as
trading goes. This one's pretty
advanced. It actually has an extra canoe
along with it.
And then here's another one. Now, they
do have steamers uh eventually coming
into the mix. Um but those are only
carrying so much stuff. So, this was a
more economical way to ship stuff down
the river. And then, of course, what
they would do once they got to the end
of the river, they would just ditch the
boat. Uh that usually be torn apart and
the wood would be used for something
else. And the guys would make their way
back up north with their cash in hand.
And then here's a map of the US. So the
Missouri River is right here. The
Mississippi is here. The Ohio River is
here. Arkansas River. There's many other
rivers. Just imagine all this flow of uh
people and goods working their way south
to New Orleans. And from there, you
could stay in New Orleans or the stuff
the people could go all the way to New
York or Europe or wherever. So it really
just opens up a lot of opportunities for
people. And interestingly enough,
Abraham Lincoln has a connection to this
point in time. So, why were Abraham
Lincoln's views on slavery more
progressive than those of many other
northerners? Well, it's because he
actually was a flatboatman on two
different occasions. Lincoln left
Illinois and traveled by flatbo. So,
Abraham Lincoln served as a flat boatman
twice in 1828 and 1831 when he was 19
and 22. It was on these journeys that he
first witnessed slavery. And in New
Orleans, he also saw a slave auction
firsthand uh which had a significant
impact on his views on slavery. Lincoln
would later recall those journeys as
essential in shaping his personal view
on slavery and the slave trade. This was
actually um a print that was made um
kind of talking about the life of
Abraham Lincoln. So, this is Lincoln
right here. And then this is a young
woman who's um these creepy guys are
feeling her uh body um and she's being
auctioned off. So, kind of see where
that's going. Um and then as far as the
Flatboat timeline, the War of 1812
ends in 1815. Um in 1814,
598 flatboats arrived in New Orleans.
They were keeping track of this. Uh
Lincoln makes his first flatboat trip in
1828. He makes a second one in 1831.
Bingham paints his painting jolly flatbo
in 1846. Here was the peak of the flatbo
trade this year 1847. 2,900
or 2792
[Music]
flatboats arrive in New Orleans. That's
a huge amount. That's many coming every
single day and week and month. Um and
then it kind of died off um before the
Civil War. It was replaced more like by
steamboats and stuff and then the Civil
War starts.
>> And just one note too, um Twain's one
one of his most controversial and but
well-known um novels, Huck Finn, really
hearkens back to this very period in
terms of river traffic um asing down the
river on essentially a flat boat of some
sort.
>> Oh yeah, thanks Patty. Um let's see and
then okay and then all right so if you
look at the United States to show you
the imp the economic impact that the
river had on and commerce river trade
and stuff on the United States 1850 uh
the seven biggest cities in the United
States of course you got the top four
New York Baltimore Boston are on the
east coast they were around for a long
time they were established the next
three are all these central
portion of the United States cities that
are along the river. So, New Orleans, we
already talked about that. Cincinnati is
along the Ohio River and St. Louis, uh
the Missouri and the Mississippi. So,
you can see, wow, uh this is where all
the people are moving to. There's jobs
and things going on here. So, it really
uh drives a lot of the economic activity
in the United States. And then this is
interesting. This is the population of
St. Louis and the population of New
Orleans uh from 1820 to 1860. And look
at how in a matter of 40 years the
population in St. Louis explodes. It
goes from 2,000 people to 160,000. New
Orleans goes from 27,000 to 169,000. Now
the rest of the area is not growing uh
anywhere near that rate. But these are
boom towns and reason being is because
of all the river traffic that's taking
place and the flat boatman is part of
that. And you if you actually travel
this area, you can still see they have
um historical mockups of what these
boats were like. Uh they're pretty
interesting to go on and visit. Uh
different museums and and historical
organizations have these here's a
smaller one. But anyway, getting back to
this, uh the Jolly Flat Boatman ended up
being a really popular print that uh
Bingham sold. So, a common way for
people to have art in their home is they
would take a famous painting and they
would make these color prints of it and
they could sell them for, you know, a
modest amount of money and then people
could hang them in their homes or look
at them or whatever. Um, so this jolly
flat boatman was really kind of designed
for like the market back east, so to
speak. Uh, and it would give people out
in the east coast like New York and
Baltimore and Philadelphia kind of a
sense of what it would be like to be
quote unquote out west because this is
before color photography and television
and the internet and all that stuff. And
so these paintings and depictions by
artists like Bingham is really the only
way that people can get a sense of what
life is like out in this part of the
country. So here's a jolly flat boat and
again you have these guys they're uh
looks like they're taking a break. They
did need a lot of labor for the boats to
um push it down the river, but once it
was going, uh it was somewhat relatively
uh easy to get it going. You just had to
kind of be on the lookout for rocks and
hazards and stuff like that. So, these
guys are taking a break, enjoying some
music and dancing. It's our central
figure here.
Bingham made a number of sketches. This
is what Patty was referring to earlier.
um he'd encounter people, make drawings
of them. He's not actually making the
painting out on the river. He's making
drawings and sketches. And then later
on, he go back to his studio and make
the finished painting. There's a closeup
of some of the figures,
other side,
our dancer,
and then down the bottom, this is where
they're storing all the stuff that
they're transporting south. Um, so
again, it was usually manufactured
goods, agricultural items, anything that
they could sell um for a profit or for
more money than was readily available
where they were at. And there you have
it. Brad, Patty, and Harry, any thoughts
on the jolly flat boat?
No, just that persistent idea that he is
inventing the image of middle America,
which at that time was the West. But I'm
saying this these visions are what it
what people think of I think in terms of
middle America.
>> Oh yeah. We talked about that before.
We're like, you know, these artists are
kind of documenting what's going on out
here. And the reason why we have these
visions or images of this time frame and
this era is because artists like Bingham
making these great paintings.
>> Yeah, it it's just so iconic.
>> Well, what about you, Brad and Harry?
>> You get the feeling from this that all
work is not work can be fun as well as
work.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> And that that isn't necessarily shown in
art usually. So, it's kind of unique
thing.
>> That is a neat point. I never thought
about that. But yeah, you're right. It's
usually work is work and play is play
and they don't intermingle.
Unless you're someone like Tina Turner
and MC Jaggers.
>> Well, it is it is that sense of
adventure. Go west, young man. You know,
because there's a life out here. Um,
even back then, they probably thought
that the the East Coast was too crowded.
Oh yeah. Well, imagine imagine people,
you know, they're back east in the city
and it's, you know, crowded and dirty
and, you know, blah blah blah and then
you see these images like, oh wow, that
looks, you know, fun and exciting and
adventure and there's opportunity. I
think I'll go out there and do that. So,
you know, it something had to prompt
these all these masses of people to
move. You know, if you go back to um
that chart that had the population
growth, I mean, somehow all these people
got the idea to move to these places in
an era before the television and
internet. And so, how are they, you
know, making those um decisions? And you
have to believe that paintings like this
probably influenced them. What about
you, Harry? Any on the Oh, go ahead,
Patty. No, I was just going to say and
it's an ingrained part of the American
uh psyche and character that movement
that, you know, you can always leave and
go somewhere else. I I think it's a part
of our character that we don't really
think about a lot.
>> Oh, yeah. No, definitely. I mean, that
is uh also an excellent point. Yeah. I
mean, hey, you know, whatever. You get
divorced, you can move somewhere else,
you lose your job, you can pack your
bags and go find a new one some other
city if you want. Um what about you,
Harry? Any thoughts on the jolly flat
boat?
>> Yeah, just um
I think somebody was asking about the
skit, you know, that below where the
level that they're on. Uh you know, he
does provide some detail. You know, you
see the bed rolls rolled up and a shirt
hanging up and it it looks like a
raccoon skin uh hanging there. He really
he tries to provide uh details to give
you know give you the impression that he
really saw it right that that that that
this is a real scene
>> um and not just something that is
totally made up. Um and you know
somebody mentioned in the comments that
he he you know he uses this triangular
formation right uh of of the the men on
the boat and when you see a lot and of
course this is something that artists
have been doing going back to classical
times right using this kind of a of a
form uh to give structure to to a
particular painting and when when you
look at a lot of Bingham's paintings of
group scenes, you see a a very similar
idea that he uses in in a lot of them.
>> Oh, yeah. That was Pamela. Shout out to
her for bringing up the triangular
composition. So, if you're not familiar
with that, okay, here's the top of the
triangle. Here's the corner. Here's the
other corner. And this is a technique
that artists use, Harry mentioned, it's
been around for a long time, but it it
just kind of makes the the artwork kind
of more uh visually appealing. It kind
of solidifies the figures and things
like that. So, it's a frequent uh art
technique. So, shout out to Pamela uh
for interjecting that. Thanks.
Appreciate that. Um let's see. So, he
does a whole series of these paintings
uh life along the Missouri River. Here's
another one at the Young Museum in San
Francisco. Boatman on the Missouri from
1846.
Um again, part of the river series. This
is a group of individuals that are
working. They don't look like they're
having quite as much fun as the last
group of guys. Um but these were called
wood hawks. And what they do, the steam
ships were going up and down the river
and they needed wood uh to operate the
ship for fires and things like that.
Well, it's not like the steam ship can
go send out a group of guys on their own
to go chop down trees. So, they would
essentially buy wood uh from these
locals that would cut it down, put it on
these little boats, take them out to the
steamers, and then sell them uh and then
kind of continue on their way. So,
interesting depiction here.
And here's a closeup.
>> Plus a smaller boat, so they're probably
uh less alcohol and food service.
>> Yeah. Right. Exactly. Um interesting.
The guy's got a top hat that on the
left.
And then here's another one. This is
called the wood boat. Similar thing.
They loading up wood to take it out to
the steamers. Part of the wood hawks of
the river series.
That's also part of that American spirit
too. This is an invention.
Um, you invented work to meet the
conditions that you were living in. And
it so it there was this improvisational
quality to the development of America in
general, I think.
>> Yeah. I mean, it's very entrepreneurial.
Hey, like, hey, my job is I'm going to
start a business. I'm going to cut down
trees and chop them up into logs and put
them on this little boat and take them
out to the steamers and sell them and
then, you know, repeat the process. So,
very entrepreneurial spirit in that
regard. Thanks, Patty. Appreciate you
mentioning that. So, again, just all
this uh commerce and trade and jobs and
stuff uh that come out of the river, the
activity and Bingham depicting that uh
through his paintings. And you know,
it's fortunate that he did because hey,
if it wasn't for this um you know, the
photography wasn't established at this
point in time, so we wouldn't have um
these types of images. Here's another
one called lighter relieving a steamboat
a ground. Um so what this boat is doing
is this one off in the distance is run
ground which means uh it needs to be
lightened or they have to lighten the
load of the boat that ran ground um so
that it'll be freed from whatever's it
got stuck in. Um and so these guys would
go out and basically unload stuff off
the boat temporarily. Um and then once
it got freed they turn around and put
the stuff back on. Um, this is
interesting because this painting is
actually in the White House and it was a
request from Lady Bird Johnson, First
Lady Lady Bird Johnson, the wife of
Lyndon Johnson. Uh, George Caleb Bingham
was one of her favorite artists and she
really wanted a painting of his to be in
the White House collection. So, she
organized that and so the
occupants of the White House can go
check out Bingham's work. Notice this
guy.
>> She was East Texas. She was East Texas,
right?
>> Yeah. She's from uh Texas, but no, she
really admired uh Bingham's artwork.
>> Texas, though, so she would have been
very aware of this culture that
developed that whole area.
>> Um let's see. Notice this guy. He's got
a hole in his sleeve. Um so just
interesting cast of characters. Here's
Rasman playing cards from 1847. Got part
of the river series. These are workers
taking a break playing cards. Um, so
kind of what they'd load the boat and
you kind of needed um maybe one or two
people to steer it because you don't
want it to go ground or you don't want
it to run into some rocks or you know a
tree stump sticking out of the water
like they call this a snag. Um the rest
of the guys though were just kind of
there to hang out until they were needed
to load the boat or unload the boat or
maybe take their turns um you know on
watch so to speak and things like that.
But time to play cards.
Here's another one in a quandry.
Mississippi grass minute cards. So you
can see how they spend their free time
playing cards and singing and dancing
and all that kind of stuff.
There's another one watching the car go.
So, what happened sometimes is the boats
would pull into an area where there
might be people living uh and it maybe
was a chance for them to go into town
and maybe buy some supplies or I don't
know get a meal or a drink or something,
but you just can't have everybody leave
the boat unattended because all your
stuff is on it. Uh so some of the guys
would stay behind and keep guards on
thing. And thus the title of this
painting, watching the cargo.
And then here's one at the National
Guard Art in Washington DC, Mississippi
Boatman from 1850. It's a character
study. It's unfortunate we don't know
who this gentleman is. Imagine if this
was someone's uh uh ancestor. Like, oh
yeah, that's my great greatgrandfather,
Bill. He was a Mississippi boatman back
in 1850. Um, but again, kind of the the
economic development of this industry
and how it affects commerce and
transportation and trade and all that
kind of stuff.
And then later on 1857,
um, Bingham does another painting of the
riverbo. And this is one of his biggest
paintings. It's 47 by 70 in. So I mean,
this painting is 4 feet high and almost
six feet wide. And by this point in
time, the flat boats have been replaced
by steamboats and even railroads. Um, so
this is kind of almost like a nostalgic
look. Um, because if you think of the
Civil War, which would start a few years
later, railroads were pretty um,
prevalent by then. Um, so this is just a
few years earlier. And so this is maybe
almost more like a nostalgic scene u,
than anything. This painting depicts a
flatbo docked a warf in St. Louis where
boatman amuse themselves with homespun.
There's that word that Patty used
earlier. Entertainment, George Caleb
Bingham has organized the crowd in a
pyramid.
Thanks to our friend Pamela's
observation earlier, with the smiling
dancer waving his red handkerchief at
its apex. So, here you go.
>> Another point made in the documentary
last night was that um he did not um
typically include um people of color in
his paintings. And yet in this one,
three years before the or four years
before the Civil War, um he included a
black figure.
>> Yeah, he does right here.
>> Um he seems slightly he's not really
connected. He's kind of just standing
there where everybody else has an
activity or is in a pose like leaning
against something.
>> Um I thought that was interesting the
way they they highlighted that in the
documentary.
>> Oh yeah. Um let's see. Here's some
figures off to the side.
And again, really nicely done.
And you may be looking at this going,
"Okay, well, you know, these are nice
paintings." Um, but you know, what's the
big deal? Well, again, there wasn't
really anybody else documenting this
stuff because they don't have
photography and there's not any other
artists really doing anything like this.
It's not like I can like, oh, hey, let
me show you all the other um paintings
of life along the river that were being
created at this point in time. Yeah,
there were some uh but no one kind of
the extent of Bingham or at least the
talent of Bingham.
And then here's another one in Chicago,
kind of a similar one. Jolly Flat Bman.
So, you're kind of seeing these like
similar themes over and over again. And
oftentimes these paintings aren't being
created for locals uh in Missouri.
They're being packed up and shipped to
the East Coast uh and sold there. that's
where the market I mean some of them
would have stayed in the local area um
but these were often made for people
back east so to speak and if you want a
great book about George Caleb Bingham's
river paintings here it is navigating
the west George Caleb Bingham and the
river you can check that out
so the river series and American
national identity let's see why don't we
start Brad with you any thoughts on
river paintings then we'll go to Harry
and Patty before we continue on to the
next section which fy be country
politics.
>> Trying to get it so I can talk this
time. Do you hear me?
>> Oh, yeah. Loud and clear.
>> Well, these these paintings are very
interesting. They're very full of
information if you parse it out
>> and they're full of uh some fun
>> and I was impressed by them.
>> Oh, thanks Brad. Appreciate that. What
about you, Harry? Any thoughts on the
river series before we go on to the next
section?
>> Uh yeah, a couple things. Uh somebody
asked about the medium and I think he
worked almost exclusively in oil
although I do think in the movie last
the you know from yesterday they
mentioned that his early portraits he
was using house paint
just because it was hard to get you know
the right
>> materials.
>> Yeah. the materials to work with. And uh
somebody mentioned a certain flatness. I
think it's more of a
the figures look more like statues. Like
he does try to show movement, right? But
there there is a certain stiffness in
the in in the in the structure of the
way the bodies are presented, right? Um,
and he uses a lot of color and he's
trying to give us a sense of movement,
right, with the dancing gear and that
kind of thing. But I I think you know
based on his not you know having very
little formal education uh you know this
is a kind of a unique style that he
developed uh in in in the way and
especially because he did so many
portraits to start with which are like
you know like you want someone to sit
still while you're painting them right
and so to transition to genre scenes um
you you you have that portrait
sensibility uh you know when you do
those paintings.
>> Oh yeah. Yeah, definitely. Thanks,
Harry. Appreciate that. What about you,
Patty? Any final thoughts on the river
series before we continue on?
>> Well, another thing that I keep noticing
in his um work after the early portraits
is this sense of light. Um it very
different from anything we've seen with
impressionists, but yet his use of light
is very important to the whole idea of
to the whole effect of these paintings.
Yeah, it really um you can I think for
myself I don't know I didn't I don't
necessarily see it right away but when
you start looking at it and processing
and thinking about like oh yeah yeah you
can tell that he wants uh he
incorporates that in a lot of his
paintings the light aspect which you
don't always see especially from uh
paintings from this era
>> and there's a very golden quality to it
which again adds to that sense of ideal
you know. Yeah, golden quality. That's a
good way to put it. So, okay. What about
anybody else thoughts?
>> I was just gonna The other thought I had
was, you know, steamboats were coming in
at this time and you and you saw in that
one painting there was a steamboat in
the far distance, right? Uh that had run
around. But, you know, his focus is
really on the the the flatbs and and the
the men who are, you know, participating
in that activity. Um, so he doesn't, you
know, he's obviously interested in a
more sort of nostalgic
um, you know, less machineoriented
uh, view of man interacting with each
other, man and and man interacting with
nature as opposed to incorporating, you
know, the steamboats or railroads in any
sign, you know, like there might be a
steamboat way in the back on that
painting. So they're they're he's
keeping them in the distance.
>> Yeah, that is an excellent point because
you kind of think like well why would he
do that? I mean this this is like this
new technology. Uh and I think it's a
different a little bit different era but
like the impressionists there's all
these paintings of trains in their
paintings because trains were a
relatively uh new thing and new
technology and so they really wanted to
incorporate that. But you would think
like oh how come he's not captivated by
the railroads and the steamboats and
stuff? he has kind of uh got this kind
of like nostalgic sense of uh kind of
documenting what's going on before this
way of life passes by.
>> Yeah, he there's there's that um
improvisational and temporary um
message that's conveyed um as we've
pointed out. I mean a lot of times these
boats you just sold them, broke them up,
whatever when you got to the end of the
river and got home a different way. So
there's a lot of temporariness about
this whole phase of American history and
how people were making their way and
making their living.
>> Right. Okay. All right. Let's continue
on. Um Bingham was a politician at
different points in time in his career.
Um and he often painted political
scenes. So let's talk about this. This
is known as either his uh country
politics series or his election series.
Um, and it's basically people going
through the democratic process. Uh,
which is also, of course, very
fascinating in terms of the American
experience. So, George Caleb Bingham,
here's another one of his self-portraits
he did. He was about 38 or 39 at this
point in time in 1849, 1850. He was in
the Missouri state legislature. He was
elected there in 1848. And throughout
his uh life, he ends up holding several
different political offices. He was
never like a governor, a congressman,
but he was more involved in politics at
the uh local and state level.
Here's a painting also from San
Francisco, country politician from 1849.
And these series are really
characterized, the paintings in these
series really characterized by Bingham
uh documenting what's known as uh say
democracy and action or how the kind of
political process works uh out in kind
of middle America in terms of like
country politics. So, here you have a
candidate and his constituents, uh, and
he's out campaigning for local political
office. Oops.
So, here you have a guy and he's giving
his spiel to these three gentlemen.
I think he's saying, "I'm not going to
raise taxes or something along those
lines." Um, here's a closeup.
Here's another one. canvasing for a vote
from 1852. This is at the Nelson Atkins
Museum of Art in Kansas City. If you
want to see Bingham's paintings up close
in person, uh the National Gallery of
Art Washington DC has some great ones,
so does the Metropolitan Museum of Art
in New York. Um but because Bingham's
from Missouri, the Nelson Atkins Museum
of Art in Kansas City and the St. Louis
Museum of Art um have fabulous
collections of his artwork. again,
democracy in action, gentleman
campaigning for local office.
And then here's one at the St. Louis Art
Museum, the country election from 1852,
uh, featuring local politics. And this
has to do with the vote casting process.
So sometimes the paintings in Bingham's
election series are candidates debating
or speaking or talking to constituents
or the the vote um processing
structure so to speak. So all different
types of the democratic process. And one
thing that people might not realize if
you're not familiar with this era, uh
elections at this point in time were big
social events. And so there was food and
alcohol and drinking and socializing. It
wasn't like today where you just show up
at the ballot, place your uh vote and
cast your vote and then leave ASAP and
go about your business. Kind of the see
all these guys hanging out. Uh looks
like this guy's enjoying the free
beverages that are being dispensed. It
looks like this guy enjoyed too many of
the beverages that were dispensed. Uh
same thing with this guy over here.
Here's
someone taking an oath. Um, I think what
he's doing here is he's swearing that he
hasn't voted anywhere else because of
course, you know, the technology back
then was um not very substantial.
And then here's another one, Stump
Speaking. This is also at the St. Louis
Art Museum. Again, local politics this
time cam painting. Uh, this painting
actually depicts George Caleb Bingham in
the painting.
I'll show you in just a moment. So, here
is actually Bingham over here. He's
included himself in this painting. Uh,
and this is a debate that's taking
place. So, this gentleman's running for
office. He's speaking to the group. And
then this gentleman's kind of waiting
his turn, taking notes.
A candidate leans forward to list his
points before a crowd of rural citizens.
Behind him sits his opponent, which just
so happens to be George Caleb Bingham,
with tablet in hand, taking notes for
his turn at the makeshift podium.
Scholars have used Bingham's drawings to
identify individuals in this work.
Although many of these figures were
recognizable to Missurrians, Bingham
intended this painting celebrating or
intended this painting celebrate the
democratic election process to more
generally for a national audience. Um,
and hey, speaking of how this parallels
with American history, so the Lincoln
Douglas debates, uh, famous historical
series of events took place, it wasn't
when Abraham Lincoln was running for
president. It was when he was running
for the United States Senate seat from
Illinois against Steven Douglas and they
had a series of debates in 1858. So this
is really a great example of life
imitating art because the Lincoln
Douglas debates took place in 1858
and the painting was from 1853 1854. So
wow, imagine that. So it's almost like
uh Bingham is depicting something that
would be playing out in real life on an
important level just a few years later.
Now of course they had debates like this
all the time uh in this era but
interesting that he captures this
And here's a closeup of some of the
figures
and unfold. Now, before we get too far
ahead, because there's a few more things
in the series, this is one of the more
well-known works um in his election
series, as is this one. Um, anybody have
any thoughts or commentary on these two
works?
Well, again, it's like it's portraying
the the uh process of America inventing
itself between one Civil War and the
next Civil War that sort of fixed some
other things. But um but it was in this
phase where we were
feeling out what it meant to be a
democratic republic, the American
experiment.
>> Yeah. Which was still a relatively new
idea at this point in time.
>> That's why it was called an experiment.
>> Yeah. was not was not established at
all.
>> Okay.
>> So, they'reing it as they go along.
>> Okay. Harry and Brad thought
>> Yeah. One of the things that this
painting points out is that there was
not a secret ballot,
right? You you that guy is is swearing
and then he's going to vote in front of
everybody.
Um, and so, uh, this this made it very
difficult to take an an opposition
position, you know, like if most of the
people in your county thought one way
and you thought the other. Yeah, that
made it very difficult for people uh,
voting the other way in in some cases.
>> Yeah, thanks for pointing that out. And
the the other thing is, you know,
there's there's a very interesting
tension here because,
you know, the the swearing of an oath
that's like a sacred thing, right? Like
you you're uh swearing to tell, you
know, this is this is sort of um you
know the of course it's not church, but
it it it's it's the most sort of sacred
part of of the democratic process,
right? you making your vote uh making
your voice known as as to what you want
to do. But he's also he's got the the
the guy holding up the drunk guy, right?
Like he's going to bring him up there so
that he can vote, right? And and the guy
here in in in, you know, sitting down on
on the the side of the painting, you
know, getting another drink um before or
after he voted. Um, so you know, he's
kind of pointing out like, yeah, this is
a really important thing, but some
people don't take it quite as seriously
and you know, some of the politicians
are involved in supplying those drinks,
right? So that they can make sure people
vote the way that he thinks they should.
>> Oh, yeah.
So, you know, there is some social
commentary going on in that
>> and that same that same social
commentary persists in the American
consciousness today and is capitalized
on regularly. And you know what's
interesting is that if if a modern if a
contemporary artist were going to do
some kind of a similar series, you know,
even though so much has gone to the
internet and television, there are still
town hall meetings that that take place
um and and politicians go to diners,
right, to to to talk to people.
>> Oh, yeah. Fast food restaurants. So, you
know,
>> Yeah. So in those days, this was the
only way that politics took place for
the for the most part. Now there there
are myriads of ways that people
communicate, but some of this one-on-one
interaction still takes place in our
time.
>> Mhm. Oh, yeah.
>> Yeah. That's that persists in our
consciousness that that this is kind of
how we came along. And so it there's
always that willingness to suspect that
there's a lot more going on than we
really know.
>> Mhm.
Yeah. And again, a great example of
artist kind of documenting uh what's
going on because it wasn't for paintings
like this. Uh I mean, you would read
about this in a book or something or
hear about it in a I don't know, History
Channel documentary, but be able to
actually see what this looked like even
if it is kind of a some partially
fictitious rendering um is really
interesting nonetheless. So, all right.
Well, let's continue on. You did a few
more
>> the substance of of Mark Twain's social
commentary and uh who was the guy Will,
you know who I mean, in the 30s. Um,
>> Frell,
>> I'm sorry.
>> Rogers. Will Frell. Will Rogers.
>> That that's this is the like the root of
that sort of social commentary that
Americans have always loved.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah.
Great point. Yep. Will Rogers. Um,
here's another famous painting from the
election series called The Verdict of
the People, St. Louis Art Museum, 1854,
1855. Again, elections of social events.
Uh, you'll notice this one, American
flag.
And then there's some women here off the
distance. Women weren't voting uh, most
likely at this point in time. And then
you also have African-American gentlemen
over here.
who also weren't
>> who also weren't voting.
>> Right. Exactly. Yeah. Um so voting was
much more limited at this point in time.
And then is this maybe guy that's also
had too much drink?
Crowds gather around a courthouse to
hear voting results. Everyone is here.
for the wellto-do farmers, laborers,
merchants, kids, politicians,
immigrants, veterans, women, and
enslaved African-Americans. George Caleb
Bingham used his personal experience in
the Missouri legislature as inspiration
for the election series, which
illustrates various stages of the
American Democratic system, such as
political campaigning and the casting of
votes. Note his inclusion of the women
in the balcony. It's back here. I'll
give you a zoom in in a minute. um and
the African-American in the left
foreground represent two populations
without a voice in government at this
time.
And so yeah, they're counting the votes
and announcing the results.
And here's the women over here
>> being kept safe from all that influence.
Yeah, I don't want to get I've read a
common thing was, you know, women don't
want to get involved in politics. It's
too dirty and and all that kind of
stuff, so to speak. So interesting in
that regard. Um, so there you have it.
The election series. Let's see. Let's
continue on. So Bingham also makes a
number of important history paintings um
which really kind of help reinforce or
shape the national identity. Here's
three great examples. Let's talk about
these.
And these particular three paintings
have to do with the American Revolution,
Manifest Destiny,
and the Civil War.
Here's the first one. This is at the
Keer Art Museum in St. Louis. Daniel
Boone escorting settlers through the
Cumberland Gap. Uh this is a painting
from 1851 to 1852. This is a really big
painting. It's over four feet wide. Uh
it's what's known as a history painting
which is a work that's documenting some
historical event. Uh this is part of the
manifest destiny where people are uh
moving west and America just feels like
it's destiny to break out from the
eastern part of the continent uh and go
coast to coast. So here you have Boone
and he's leading a group of individuals
through the Cumberland Gap. Now, Daniel
Boone is an interesting figure uh in the
sense that he plays a really important
role in American history. Uh and he was
known as an important figure for a
really long time, but I do feel like in
the last few decades, people have kind
of forgotten um about him. So, we'll
talk about that in just a moment. Here's
Manifest Destiny. Okay, so United States
starts off in the 13 colonies, works its
way west, and then eventually people
start saying, "Hey, you know, uh we
should just be content to be over in
this eastern part of the US. we should
have this whole uh continent from coast
to coast at least in this part of the
hemisphere.
The Cumberland Gap is a pass within the
Appalachian Mountains and near the
trioint of Kentucky, Virginia, and
Tennessee, long used by Native American
nations. In 1775,
Daniel Boone led a team of frontiersmen
to widen the path through the Cumberland
Gap to make settlement of Kentucky and
Tennessee easier. By the 1790s, the
trail that Boon and his men built had
been widened to accommodate wagons,
making it accessible to pioneers who
used it to journey into the western
frontiers of Kentucky and Tennessee. And
you can actually visit this area. So,
here's the Cumberland Gap right here.
So, here's Virginia, Tennessee, and
Kentucky. And so, people are moving.
There's this big um series of mountains
through here. It makes it difficult to
travel through here, at least at this
point in time. but they could go through
the gap and get into fertile Kentucky
and Tennessee. Um, and again, so Daniel
Boone, he's like a really important guy
in American history. Uh, in fact, at one
point in time, he even had like an own
television show about him. Uh, I'm
guessing that if they were to come out
with a television show about Daniel Boon
now that it would be a big dud because
unless it had like, I don't know, Brad
Pitt in it or Johnny Depp or something
because um I don't and I don't have any
idea why, but he's just not as popular
for whatever reason uh as he was. But
yeah, was and this was a well-known
television show was really popular at
the time, but uh I don't think they
would do this anymore for I don't know
why, whatever reason. Um he's just been
kind of forgotten about. And of course
remember uh Chester Harding, he had done
the painting of Daniel Boone that um our
good friend George Caleb Bingham saw
when he was a young man.
And then that painting that Bingham saw
as a child ended up being the profile
photo of Daniel Boone's Wikipedia page.
Uh note here, one of the first folk
heroes of the United States. And it
talks about the Cumberland cap in case
you're wondering Boon's famous. I think
a lot of people have heard of Daniel
Boone. They know he was like from the,
you know, earlier times, but not quite
sure what exactly he did or why he's
famous. I'm guessing if you had to maybe
survey people.
Um, here's the painting again
and then the description of it. The
narrative paintings of George Caleb
Bingham were influential in crafting
political ideologies and popular myths
about American national identity in the
era of westward expansion. Here, Bingham
uses Christian iconography to celebrate
Daniel Boone and his explorations of the
American West 75 years earlier.
Specifically, his entrance into the
western territories of Kentucky and
Tennessee. Boon is shown emerging with
his caravan from a forboating valley
into the dramatic light of the
foreground. Evoking Moses leading his
people towards the promised land. Boon's
wife sits prominently at top a white
horse. There she is. Um, with a shaw
draped around her body and head. The
triumphant passage of the group through
the landscape with its sublime valley,
menacing cliffs, and storm damaged trees
lends further authority to their
civilizing mission symbolically
sanctioning westward expansion.
All right. So there's the full view of
the painting
>> giving some solidity to the whole
concept of manifest destiny.
>> Yeah, exactly. Then they have that
triangular composition again. And here's
Boon, the man. He's leading these people
to the promised land. And even the dog
is coming along. And then you notice the
painting in the sides in the back. It's
really dark, but he's coming into the
light, so to speak. So interesting
picture there. Uh let me go through
these other history paintings, then
we'll check in with um you guys, Harry,
Brad, and Patty. Uh this is at the
Chrysler Museum of Art, Norfol,
Virginia. I used to live not far from
here and visit here all the time. It's a
great museum uh in southeastern Virginia
in the Hampton Roads Tidewater area. You
get a chance, you should check that out.
And this is Washington crossing the
Delaware. He actually worked on this
painting for several years. He started
in 1856. He tweaked it for many years
and didn't finish till 1871. It's a
depiction of the American Revolution,
the important Battle of Trenton, which
took place in December of 1776.
Washington crossing the Delaware.
There's another painting that you've
probably seen of the same topic was done
a few years earlier. So, here's
Bingham's work
and here is
information on this event. So, a
defining moment in American history. In
the months after the Declaration of
Independence on July 4th, 1776, George
Washington's army had been enduring
months of defeats and retreats. And then
finally, this event took place. A
momentum changer, a decisive American
military victory that turned the tide of
the American Revolution and world
history. Washington crossing the
Delaware and the Battle of Trenton.
And prior to the Oh, go ahead.
>> No, this one is very different from the
painting that most people think of when
they think of the a portrait of
Washington Cross in the Delaware.
>> Oh, yeah. And I'll show that painting
just a minute. You have to remember uh
the time that this was painted, George
Washington was the most famous American
uh before the end of the Civil War. And
I don't even know who would be number
two. There probably wasn't even a number
two. It was like him and then everybody
else. And so uh you could do well by
painting George Washington. Here's the
more famous depiction of Washington
Cross in Delaware. That's also at the
Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York.
And this is also a fabulous painting.
>> This is the more European version. And
the the Bingham one is the more American
version.
>> Yeah. And I've heard someone say the one
the one on the left. Well, I like both
of these paintings. I'm not I as I say
before, I never try and show these to um
say that one is better than the other.
Um just to kind of highlight comparisons
and contrast. Um that being said, both
of these are really cool. I heard
someone one time say that the one on the
left is more the Hollywood version. Uh
it wasn't really, you know, like that.
um that maybe the Bingham one might be a
little bit more kind of uh uh realistic.
Although Washington wasn't a stride his
horse uh when he was crossing the river,
but it also wasn't like, you know,
George Washington was on like the lead
boat,
you know, with everything going on in
the background either. So, okay, there
that term artistic liberties is a real
thing. What's that, Patty?
>> It's our sense of ourselves. Um, you
know, on the one side we were taking on
Europe because we were just as good as
Europe, and on the the Bingham side, we
are being American. It's it's it there's
just a different sensibility to the two
different portraits.
>> Oh, yeah. And, you know, you also have
to do remember too, as famous as this
painting was, it wasn't like the artist
made it and then immediately everybody
knew about it. I mean, things traveled,
information traveled much slower back
then. So for him to make this painting
be like, you know, pick picture someone
in Missouri who's never seen that other
painting before and don't has no idea
what this event looked like, even if
they've heard about it. Like, oh, okay,
that's what it was like to be with, you
know, Washington when he was crossing
the Delaware. That's cool. So, um, you
know, it kind of served its purpose, um,
so to speak.
>> So, yeah,
>> that's what I mean. the identity.
Developing the identity.
>> And he has a good flatbo in in the
Bingham painting.
>> Exactly.
>> Thanks, Harry. Appreciate that. Um,
let's see. Oh, if you want to actually
see this event, they do a reenactment
every year of Washington Cross in the
Delaware. It's really cool. These are
actually what the boats look like. They
don't look like the depictions in the
paintings. Um, but you know, hey, how
would how would George Caleb being in
Missouri know what these plat uh these
boats looked like that Washington used
um several years earlier?
>> Didn't Washington um requisition
civilian whatever was available
civilian?
>> Yeah, he basically got these private
boats and u and come
uh let's see. Oops. Oh, if you want to
learn more about Washington Crossing,
Delaware, there's this really cool movie
called The Crossing, starring Jeff
Daniels as George Washington. We've
streamed it before and we're going to do
it again on Saturday evening, December
13th, and it's part of our um American
Revolution 250th anniversary programs
we'll be doing in the near future.
Um, let's see.
Any more thoughts on but I guess maybe
we can um take a little bit of a break
from me talking um just because these
paintings were important. Any thoughts
on the um Daniel Boone and the
Cumberland Gap or
George Washington? Well, Jeff Jeff had
pointed out that like me, he keep he
gets uh David Crockett and Daniel Boone
um mixed.
I believe Parker played both characters
in different productions, which might be
one reason why we can't tell the
difference.
>> Oh, I see. Okay. Well, no, that's fair
enough.
>> And it was David Crockett supposedly
wore the skin cap, but you tell me
what kind of cap Daniel Boon is wearing
in this these pictures. Mhm.
>> Looks kind of cool and skinny to me.
>> Yeah, I don't know. Good question.
Did somebody else have something?
No, just the in the Boon painting I
looking at it again, you know, I was
struck by
his his his wife on the horse wearing
the shawl, you know, it's it's a very um
it's very much a religious, you know,
the idea of a
you know, Mary in the PA or you know,
>> Yeah. very biblical.
>> Yeah. looks has a very it's it's a very
biblical sort of throwback
>> and this yeah this painting gives me a
little bit of a chill because I really
the whole idea of manifest destiny like
just doesn't strike a good chord with me
and yet this is like you say giving it
the Bible
>> um let's see then any thoughts on this
one
>> well as I said this is really the the
middle west American version of
Washington Cross in the Delaware.
>> I'm sure it was every bit as as strong a
story um in Bingham's time, but like you
said, most of these people had not seen
more European style art.
>> All right, let's continue on. And then
he made another famous historical
>> donated
>> um let's see. So, um, Bingham's living
in Missouri and in the years before,
during, and after the Civil War, uh,
there's all this death and destruction
taking place just because of the, um,
uh, people debating slavery and kind of
related issues to that. Um, these are
not Bingham paintings. These are other
artists, um, we'll talk about in the
future, but Bingham does make a
painting. It's at the Cincinnati Art
Museum. It's called Order Number 11.
They spent a lot of time in the
documentary talk about this. That was
kind of one of the things that um I was
not crazy about the documentary, the
fact that they spent so much time
talking about this. I did like the fact
that they talked about it, but it just
seemed like they kind of went on and on
and on about this one particular
painting. Um and maybe went over a few
other topics, but anyway, that's my
personal opinion. I did really like the
documentary. That was my only complaint.
Um this is a big painting. It's 79 in
wide. Uh usually in art scale oftentimes
represents importance. So this is a very
important painting by Bingham and it's a
history painting about the Civil War.
And so there's all this conflict taking
place um again before, during and after
the Civil War uh between pro-slavery and
anti-slavery
individuals. Things kind of come to a
head here. Um you can see these are some
Union soldiers. Um these are basically
the people that are being like kicked
out of their house um because people
were had to be cleared from here. Uh,
this woman here has lost her I'm
assuming that's her husband. Um, here's
some African-Americans are kind of
turning away. Uh, need smoke in the
background. Some things have been set on
fire.
And then you can see general order
number 11 is the title of the Union Army
directive issued during the American
Civil War on August 25th, 1863, forcing
the abandonment of rural areas in four
counties in western Missouri. uh they
ordered this because the rebels were uh
kind of running rampant so to speak in
these areas. So it's kind of a way for
them to clear them out
and so was a controversial topic for
Bingham to depict.
And then
oops here's a closeup of the figures on
the right. And so you know they're
bringing their furniture and stuff
outside because they have to leave. you
just can't leave all your possessions
behind. And so that's what's being
depicted here.
And any thoughts on this one?
>> I thought it was really interesting in
the documentary that uh one of the
curators said
refugees. It's not something you think
of in America and I immediately thought
of the founding myth that we most
celebrate the pilgrims, right? We're
refugees.
And from that point on, refugees in
America was a constant theme. And yet,
we literally do not think of it as
refugees. What did we rename those
people? Pilgrims. We gave them biblical
force. It's just really interest. It
just caught me when she said, "You don't
think of refugees as being an American
theme." And I'm like, "Wait a minute.
It's very American."
>> Yeah. They had to re rebrand them. Um,
what about Brad and Harry? Any thoughts
on this painting?
>> Well, I this painting is is kind of
important in in Bingham's life because
it's it's really his most overtly
political statement
and he was pro- Union. Somebody asked
about how how he felt about the the
Civil War. He was he was pro- Union. But
what this is a very controversial event
where the Union general is bringing the
the red legging those are guys those are
pro-UN guys from Kansas
and of course the background of this you
know Missouri was one of the four slave
states that did not go to the
Confederacy right they didn't join the
Confederacy
so people are very divided and before
the war, the next state over, the next
territory over is Kansas. And Kansas
becomes the killing ground for pro and
anti-slavery people before the Civil War
breaks out. So, we're looking at an area
of the country where there had been
violence going back into the 1850s ba
based on uh the the the the politics of
slavery happening in the Congress. Uh,
and
it's it's so interesting to me that this
is the only Civil War painting that he
made. Um, and that he's depicting a
scene which is is very critical of of an
of a decision that a Union general has
made. Um because he's showing this guy
from can the the Kansas and the
Missurrians did not like each other even
though they were on the the the Union
supporters were on the same side in the
war. And a lot of people felt like the
guy these the guys with the red leggings
from Kansas were like thugs that were
brought in to evacuate everybody uh so
that the the rebels wouldn't have any
resources. Um, and so
now Bingham, you know, they talked in
the movie about his house that got used
to hold Confederate women that collapsed
and a number were killed. And I think he
was very bitter about that situation
because he hadn't the the Union uh army
had just taken over his house. Um, and I
think I his his bitterness about stuff
that happened be, you know, before and
during the war kind of spilled over into
this painting. And a lot of people were
very critical of what he had done here
because they thought he was a
Confederate supporter because he was con
he was uh condemning something that the
Union government had done during the
war. Um,
>> oh yeah, it's like if if you're pro-
union, how could you possibly u uh
challenge any anything criticize
anything at all the union has done?
Shame on you.
>> And and and and he, you know, he had
prints of this made. I mean, he he
wanted this message to get out. Um, but
a lot of uh his pro-UN, you know,
friends and contacts really were very
critical of him because of this
painting. And it I I think it it uh
hampered his ability to um you know his
creative ability later in life.
>> Oh yeah. It really impacted his
commissions that he received later. I
mean I guess a more modern be like
someone making a painting of the My
Massacre in Vietnam and wondering why
people would be so outraged about it. So
>> yeah.
>> Well, and this is a central bill of
rights question. I mean issue. These
people were being deprived of their
rights as citizens in the name of the
United States of America.
>> And that is such a crux issue that yes,
we have never really dealt well with we
don't do that, but we do when we do it.
You know what I mean? It's
>> there's that.
>> Well, yeah. The internment camps with
the Japanese during
tension and it's coming back again. You
know, it's here now again. And I mean it
it's it's so interesting because it's
like you know not doing any paintings of
railroads or steamboats. This is the
only Civil War painting he did.
>> Exactly.
>> So you know but but there was a huge
amount of violence going on in his part
of the country leading up to and during
the war. Right. So the fact that that
this was his choice um you know really
says something about how something
happened during the war that had a huge
impact on him.
>> Oh yeah because remember like the
Winslow Homer Civil War paintings
they're like soldiers you know hanging
out in camps and stuff. Um you know or
even just you don't really see things
like this in this era time frame
>> because it's part of our secret pact
with each other. We don't talk about
those,
>> right? Yeah. Yeah.
>> So, okay. Well, let's continue on. Um,
so again, history paintings and then
let's look at some of his other works or
later works. Uh, these are just kind of
like a variety of different things that
he did later in life
>> and they were affected by the damage to
his reputation. I mean, the same
>> he took a huge he took a huge economic
hit. Um, I mean before before the Civil
War, he was actually pretty prosperous.
I mean, he wasn't a millionaire, but he
was very successful financially. After
the Civil War, he really struggled
financially. Um, now maybe part of that
was changing artistic tastes. Um, but
also too, just the the kind of damaged
his reputation. Anyway, I like this
painting a lot. First, I don't know why,
but it's kind of cute. The mill boy from
1844. So, this was before the Civil War.
and a young boy taking mill off or
taking um grain off to the mill. Here's
a portrait of his second wife. So, his
first wife died in 1848. Uh you might be
shocked to see that he married remarried
the following year. That was pretty
common place back then, especially if
someone had children because it would
very difficult for someone to raise
children by themselves. Um so, you
frequently see that
>> somebody
>> What's that? I said they didn't want to
pay somebody for it,
>> right? Yeah, exactly. Um, so here's his
second wife, Eliza,
and a really nice portrait of her.
And then this is at my former employer,
the Detroit Institute of Arts, the
Checker Players. It's a nice genre scene
of country life. You have two gentlemen
playing checkers with another person
looking on
Oops.
And then he did some landscapes. He's
not really known as a landscape artist,
but he did do some that were really
nice. Uh, including this one, which is
the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston
landscape with waterhe and boy fishing
from 1853.
Here's the boy fishing.
Here's the waterhe. So, really nicely
done. So, um you wouldn't want to type
cast him as just the portrait river
painting, you know, election series kind
of guy. You could do a few other
different things.
Here's a nice portrait of a young girl
later in life. Pretty cool when um they
know the identities of these people. So,
this is Miss Annie Allen, 1859, age six.
Here
is Major James Rollins. This was the guy
that he did the portrait early on his
career. He became friends with him and
then he introduced Rollins did to a
number of other prominent individuals.
He ended up getting a lot of commissions
from that. Um they stayed friends
together uh throughout the rest of their
lives. He was a politician and a lawyer.
I think they said in the in the
documentary that he continued to support
him even after the controversy.
>> Oh yeah. Yep. Um let's see. Here's an
interesting one. So later on his career,
he kind of experiments periodically with
different things. So this is if I wasn't
familiar that Bingham painted this work.
I would have never guessed this was one
of his uh paintings. But that being
said, he did this on thread and spindle
from the Civil War era. And people
thought that maybe it was prompted by
the birth of his son.
Bingham had several children during his
lifetime.
Uh this is I think his best post civil
war portrait. This is Fanny Smith
Krenshaw from 1869.
She was the wife of a prominent merchant
and businessman.
And I just feel like this portrait's
really advanced and very skilled. and he
did a lot of portraits throughout his
career, about 500 um including many
after the Civil War, but in my opinion u
this is one of his best portraits he did
during his lifetime. It's got great
details, all the intricacies of her
clothing.
And then
uh some people think this is like a
marital portrait um but it's actually a
brother and sister portrait.
Miss BW Clark, Mary Jane Kenny, and her
brother.
They were from St. Louis.
And then here's James Rollins again. Got
that cool beard.
And here's different portraits of
Rollins throughout the years.
This one is in a private collection, so
the photograph of it is not very good.
But I do really like this painting. Um,
you know, he did all those of the
election series. This one is more of
like a legal painting. It's a called
Puzzled Witness from 1874.
And then here's one of his sons.
>> Oh, named after Rollins. Yeah,
thanks for pointing that out, Patty. Um,
yeah, so I mean that shows you how close
he was to Rollins. He names one of his
sons after him.
And then Benny Ree was a sculptor based
in Washington DC for part of her career.
She did sculpture of Lincoln among
others. And she became friends with
Bingham. So he did her portrait
not once but twice. And here she is
playing some music.
And then here's a self-portrait of
Bingham. He's age 66 at this point in
time.
And you'll notice he did this portrait
in 1877. He's getting toward the later
years of his life because he passed away
in 1879. Here he's depicting himself as
an artist. He's got
pen here
and some type of drawing material.
And there you have it. George Caleb
Bingham, the Missouri artist. So, let's
do this. Let's go quick review of the
work. So, we saw the portraits from
early in his career.
Then we saw the American River series
and talked about how that shaped the
American national identity.
Then we talked about country politics
via the election series and the American
experience.
Talked about history paintings and the
American national identity and then his
later works. So why don't we do this? Um
so we'll wrap things up in just a
moment. Before we do, let's check in
with our once again distinguished panel.
Brad, why don't we start with you? Any
um final thoughts on George Caleb Bing
before we call it a night?
Oh, let's come back to Brad. Harry, why
don't we go with you?
Uh, he's, you know, he's not one of the
sort of real really well-known American
artist, right? But I think he really,
you know, because of the time period
that he's working in and where he's
working, um, he really gives us a
like a really interesting look at what
was going on in the country in in the
time that he was working. Um and you
know some of those scenes which you know
took place before photography for the
most part. Um that that you know we we
would never sort of understand or
appreciate without uh his work and the
fact that you know he was virtually
uneducated in art until later in his
life. Um, you know, it he he produced
really an an incredible body of work
that there's a lot a lot to appreciate
in what he did.
>> Yeah, I mean, uh, how do we know what
things looked like before photography if
nothing else?
>> I thoroughly agree, Harry.
>> I to me too. I can't escape this
feeling. I he seemed like somebody who
despite some hardships in his life
because he lost a lot of people um his
father died when he was young. He lost a
wife and a son. Um so but he maintained
this idealism about the idea of America
and only to have his heart broken at
that crucial time I think. And so I I
just have this sense of sadness about
him that that uh that his heart was
broken at, you know, at a crucial time.
>> Oh, you know, that is a really excellent
point, Patty, because um we didn't
discuss it here, but they talked about
um Okay, so he won that one local
election, but then he had it taken away
from him. And like you said, his father
died when he was a young man. Uh he was
married three times because uh two of
his spouses passed away. um
children died. Yeah. I mean um you know
this whole thing with the Civil War and
his house collapsing.
He has all these heartbreaking moments
uh with America but yet he kind of keeps
the faith and kind of continues uh
moving forward so to speak
>> until that constitutional crisis kind of
issue you know and that seems to have
really broken his spirit.
>> Yeah. The straw that broke the camel's
back so to speak. He he does be he does
become the first professor of art at at
the University of Missouri after
>> after it's founded. So, you know, he
does reach a level of sort of
recognition uh in his career.
>> Yeah. And then going back to the video
that we saw from the vet where uh um so
I'm guessing if you were to talk to
someone like say 120 years ago Bingham
like to Harry's point he's not a super
famous artist but it's not like he's
unknown. he was more much more obscure
um up until like the like it was almost
like he was kind of forgotten about
because you know at some point in time
America was like oh okay we're you know
they were in the guilded age and this
all this stuff is oldfashioned and you
know they want to move forward and
they're making cars and flying airplanes
and you know get involved in global
stuff and you know I'm assuming that
this for a lot of people this was like
too you know antique and you know past
tense and stuff so he was not uh he kind
of lost a lot of popularity for a while.
It wasn't until maybe the past like
hundred or so years he's really been
kind of rediscovered.
>> Yeah. And
>> you know
>> in some ways those those scenes with the
small groups, you know, and like on the
the the two men on the on the the river
boat. Um some of those are very
intimate, right? like like you're you're
getting a view of, you know, something
that's going on in a in a small group,
you know, like a personal conversation.
Um, and you know, some of those
paintings are are very striking in in
their their ability to communicate
across, you know, more than a century uh
of time.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. Documenting things.
What about Pad? Patty, Brad, Harry, any
final thoughts because we'll wrap things
up in just a moment.
>> That the f the painting of the uh two
guys pay playing playing checkers and
the one looking on. Again, I I keep
associating these paintings with
different aspects of things Twain said
or wrote. But you could almost see the
Where's the part in Huckleberry Finn
where you've got the fraudster that he's
a professor or something? almost see
them, the three of them, you know, there
and it's like, oh, yeah. Okay. Yeah. So,
you wonder if Twain called the painting
before he invented those people.
>> Yeah. I don't know. That's a very good
question. Good observation. Um, let's
see.
>> I wonder if Brad's exhausted from all
the adventures of the day.
>> I'm here.
>> Oh, okay. Hey Brett, any final thoughts
on George Caleb Bingham before we call
it a night?
>> No, I think I we pretty well done a
pretty good job of covering him
>> and uh he's these beautiful river shots,
these beautiful home shots and the the
playing checkers uh or I guess it was
checkers didn't look like chess.
Pieces weren't big enough.
It was a previous program at the live A,
but I forgot to make a joke at the end.
I was going to say, "All right, well,
that was so much fun. Why don't we just
start from the beginning and do it all
over again after a two-minute break?"
>> It's been a great day, though. Really?
>> Well, thank you. I appreciate that. And
thanks for all your help. Um, oh, Harry,
uh, one last question for you. Um, I
know you said they weren't uh official,
but did you maybe want to once again um
mention the tours that you might be
doing upcoming in the near future?
>> Well, yeah, just watch the Washington DC
history and culture and the u museum and
and embassy visit sites. Uh, and uh
hopefully I'll post something in August
and certainly in September uh for the
ending of the Second World War 80th
anniversary. I definitely want to do
something then.
>> Okay. Well, excellent. Thank you.
Appreciate that. Um, so let's see. I've
been recording this program. I'll post
the it on our YouTube channel. It might
take me a few days to do so. Uh, once
I've done that though, I'll be happy to
email out the link. If you're interested
in more art and history programs, you
can find them of our YouTube channels,
which are Washington DC History and
Culture and Texas History and Culture.
Um, as far as future art programs, um,
I'm currently working like really long
hours and so some of the stuff between
now and the end of July, so some of the
things that are on the calendar maybe,
um, have to change the date. One program
I know that's not going to have a date
change is this one. Um, so on Thursday
evening, July 4th, I was going to do a
program about the American collection at
the Detroit Institute of Arts, which is
a really excellent um, collection of
American art, including works by John
Singer, Sergeant here on the left, and
Frederick Church here on the right. So,
you can join us for that. And then this
was a two-part program. We watched a
video about George Caleb Bingham last
night, and then today we did the
lecture. We're doing a similar setup in
September. We're doing the encore of
Frederick Remington in the American
West. We'll see a documentary on him on
Friday evening, September 5th, and a
lecture on the following night,
Saturday, September 6th. This is not
completely on our calendar yet, but you
can go ahead and um note that down and
I'll send the information in the near
future. Um let's see. I one one last
thing to clarify. Um Ellen had asked I
I'm pretty sure she meant Harry's uh the
two things Harry was talking about.
There's those are not online events,
right, Harry?
>> No, no, I I only do in-person events.
So, except when I contribute to one of
Robert's,
>> right? Somebody asked the question. I
just
>> The book club.
>> Well, yes. And we have the book club.
>> Are there any are there any book club
events coming up?
>> So, we meet uh at the second Tuesday of
every month uh at 7. And for August,
we're actually going to do something
different where we're asking people to
watch a movie or a TV series or a
documentary and uh on history either uh
world history or American history and be
prepared to speak about it and uh we'll
have some discussion on different you
know shows that people have watched.
>> Oh, that's cool. And if someone's
interested in that, you can join it
virtually. Just Google um some of you
are probably already familiar with the
meetup, but if you're not in DC, um just
Google Washington DC History and Culture
Meetup or Washington DC History and
Culture Book Club or something like
that. Um you can find it. So, all right.
Well, thanks for everyone for joining
us, especially our panelists. Um I
thought I'd do this close out with one
last video. This is our preview of our
Frederick Remington program. So, oops.